A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Governance and Civil Society, Office Files of Jacqueline Berrien FA1726
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Governance and Civil Society, Office Files of Jacqueline Berrien
1965-2003
Rockefeller Archive Center
Berrien, Jacqueline A.
Ford Foundation
FA1726
3.89 Cubic Feet 10 Hollinger boxes
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas. During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Arrangement
Collection consists of one series.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Subject files, 1965-2003
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
When requesting to view audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011.
This material was transferred to the RAC in 2019 in two different sets of records and was ingested by the RAC as Accession 2019:150 and Accession 2019:177.
Accessions continue as necessary
Biographical / Historical
Jacqueline Berrien (1961-2015) was a lawyer, foundation program officer, and Chairwoman of the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (EEOC) under President Barack Obama. Between 2001 and 2004, she worked as a Program Officer in the Ford Foundation's Governance and Civil Society Program (GCS). In this position she managed a grant portfolio for projects related to Participation and Representation in American Politics.
Prior to joining the Ford Foundation, Berrien worked as a lawyer at the American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) (1987-1992), the Lawyer's Committee for Civil Rights Under Law (1992-1994), and the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People Legal Defense and Education Fund (NAACP LDF) (1995-2001). She returned to the NAACP LDF as Associate Director-Counsel in 2004 after leaving the Foundation. She was then appointed to be the Chair of the EEOC by President Obama in 2009.
Berrien was born in Washington, D.C. on November 28, 1961. She earned her BA from Oberlin College in 1983 and then earned her Doctor of Law from Harvard Law School in 1986.
Scope and Contents
Collection contains the office files of Ford Foundation Program Officer Jacqueline Berrien. Working in the Governance and Civil Society (GCS) unit of the Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Berrien managed a grant portfolio for projects concerning Participation and Representation in American Politics. The grants encompassed within this portfolio fell under two initiatives: 1) Democracy and Diversity; and 2) Reclaiming Politics for the Public. Projects related to the Democracy and Diversity initiative focused on ensuring the right to vote to more of the American public and increasing diverse participation and representation in politics. Projects related to the Reclaiming Politics for the Public initiative focused on empowering the voting public and encouraging its interest in politics.
The collection consists of one series of Berrien's subject files. These files chiefly contain research and news on subjects concerning Berrien's grant portfolio as well as materials documenting the drafting of a Program Officer Memo (POM) Berrien wrote in 2003. Ford Foundation Program Officers used the POMs to communicate the course of action they sought to take with their grant portfolios. Although Berrien served in the GCS only between 2001 and 2004, there are materials within the collection that date back to as early as 1965. These documents were submitted to and retrieved by Berrien as research material for her work. They concern topics relevant to her grant portfolio such as voting rights and electoral redistricting and mainly consist of memos, reports, and publications. In addition to these types of records and the drafts and notes showing Berrien's writing and editing of her POM, there are also news articles, brochures, correspondence, and one audio tape in the collection. Other topics discussed within the collection include felony disenfranchisement, political participation of racial and ethnic minorities, women, and youth, political representation of minorities and women, electoral campaign finance reform, and the 2000 United States presidential election.
Ford Foundation; Apportionment (Election law); Campaign funds; Elections; Political participation; Race discrimination; Representative government and representation; Voting; Voting research
- Subject files, 1965-2003; 1; 3.89 Cubic Feet 9 LTR and 1 LGL size Hollinger boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Series contains the subject files Ford Foundation Program Officer Jacqueline Berrien created during her time in the Governance and Civil Society (GCS) unit of the Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ). The files mainly consist of research and news submitted to, retrieved by, and collected by Berrien for the purpose of her duties managing a grant portfolio for Participation and Representation in American Politics as well as drafts, notes, and other materials showing Berrien's writing and editing of a Program Officer Memo (POM). Berrien wrote this POM in 2003 to describe her course of actions for achieving the objectives of her grant portfolio.
  Other types of materials found through out the series include reports, memos, news articles, brochures and correspondence. The records in the series discuss subjects such as voting rights, redistricting, felony disenfranchisement, political participation of racial and ethnic minorities, women, and youth, political representation of minorities and women, electoral campaign finance reform, and the 2000 United States presidential election.
  - Memos and articles, 2002-2003 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Governance and Civil Society (GCS) Program Officer Memos (POMs), 1999-2003 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - Meetings, schedule, and Berrien Program Officer Memo (POM), 2000-2003 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Voter redistricting, 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 8-10)
    - Redistricting No. 2, 2002 May 22; 1/4 inch audio cassette (Tape AV 10000)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
      Joint Center for Political and Economic Studies Conference – Redistricting, 1992-2002: Voting Rights and Minority Representation Mayflower Hotel, Washington, D.C., May 22, 2002 Tape 4 Panel A: Legal and Political Issues Panel B: Black, Hispanic, and Partisan Perspectives on Redistricting - Jacqueline Berrien, Leobardo Estrada, Robert Holmes, David Lublin
  - Reflection memos, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ) Program Officer Memos (POMs), 1999-2003 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - News stories, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Harvard Law School Appleseed Electoral Reform Project Workshop on Campaign Reform Project, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - The Art of Anonymous Activism: Serving the Public While Surviving Public Service, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - A World on the Move: A Report of the 2001 United Nations World Conference Against Racism, Racial Discrimination, Xenophobia, and Related Intolerance, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Voting rights restoration, 1998-2003 (Box 3, Folder 17-20)
  - Voter redistricting research, 1991-2003 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Political participation, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Children's Defense Fund (CDF), 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Women of Color Policy Network, 2001-2003 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Senator Mitch McConnell v. Federal Election Commission (FEC) - Defendant-Intervenors' Excerpts of Opposition Brief of Defendants, undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - New California Media (NCM) - Ethnic Media Outreach Campaign, undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Reports and publications - Political participation and media, 2000-2001 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Voter redistricting research, 1987-1991 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Alliance for Justice - Foundation Advocacy: How to Engage in and Support Non-Profit Advocacy workshop, 1999-2002 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Articles - Race and gender, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Brennan Center for Justice - Felony disenfranchisement, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Judicial system, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Reports and articles - Felony disenfranchisement, 2001-2002 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - United Nations Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights - Seminar on the Interdependence Between Democracy and Human Rights, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Public Campaign - The Color of Money: Campaign Contributions and Race, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars - Women's Rights in Theory and Practice: Employment, Violence, and Poverty, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Articles - Elections and political participation, 2002-2003 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Gender and governance, 1995-2002 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Reports and articles - Diversity and political participation, 1997-2002 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Liz Abzug - Women and Public Life, 1995 October (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Sherrilyn A. Ifill biography, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Articles and publications - Elections and political participation, 2001-2002 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Public Policy Institute of California - How Race, Ethnicity, and Immigration Shape the California Electorate, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Articles - Diversity and political participation, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Women and politics, undated (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Ford Foundation - Diversity, 1985-1999 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Articles - Diversity and political participation, 2001-2002 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - South Dakota Native Americans' voting rights lawsuit, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Berrien Program Officer Memo (POM) outline, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Berrien Program Officer Memo (POM) notes, 1967-2002 (Box 6, Folder 50-51)
  - Prison Reform Advocacy Center (PRAC) and voter redistricting materials, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - Voter redistricting, 1986-1992 (Box 6, Folder 53-55)
  - Voter redistricting, 1990-1991 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Reports and proposals, 2002-2003; File contains digital media. Digital media is a floppy disk. (Box 7, Folder 57-58)
  - Program Officer Memo (POM), undated (Box 7, Folder 57)
    Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
  - Program Officer Memo (POM) related materials, 1967-2000 (Box 7, Folder 59-60)
  - Program Officer Memo (POM) related materials, 2000-2003 (Box 7, Folder 61)
  - The Grantmaker Forum on Community and National Service - From Inspiration to Participation: A Review of Perspectives on Youth Civic Engagement, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 62)
  - Program Officer Memo (POM) related materials, 1985-2003 (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - Program Officer Memo (POM) related materials, 1985-2003 (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - Berrien Program Officer Memo (POM) - Drafting, 1999-2003 (Box 8, Folder 65-69)
  - Berrien Program Officer Memo (POM) - Drafting, 1986-2001 (Box 9, Folder 70-71)
  - Gender and governance, 1993-2002 (Box 9, Folder 72-73)
  - Ford Foundation - American Governance Seminar, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 74)
  - Marcia Smith exit memo and Program Officer Memo (POM), 2000 (Box 9, Folder 75)
  - Berrien Program Officer Memo (POM) - Drafting, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 76-77)
  - Gender and governance, 2001-2002 (Box 10, Folder 78-80)
  - Ford Foundation Archives search - Voting rights, 1965-1997 (Box 10, Folder 81-84)